CHAPTER 9

The English Company Export of
Slaves from Madras to St. Helena
Colony in South Atlantic (1654-1712)
and from Madras to Bengkulu in
Sumatra (1682-1748)

The English settled in Chennapattinam (Madras) in 1639. The company officials noticed the active trade conducted by the Portuguese and the Dutch on the Tamil Coast and so they desired to participate in it. But the slave dealers in Madras like Kannappa had acted as an important broker of slaves for the Dutch East India Company in Pulicat.1 Hence in the absence of native brokers it was found difficult to obtain slaves.

THE ENGLISH COMPANY EXPORT OF SLAVES FROM
MADRAS TO ST. HELENA ISLAND FOR SUGAR
PLANTATIONS IN SOUTH ATLANTIC, 1654-1712

St. Helena Island located in the South Atlantic had been a key port of call for European vessels making the arduous return journey from Asia because it was one of the few places where they could replenish their supplies of food and water safely. Due to the strategic importance of the island, the English Company occupied St. Helena and established an English colony there. As the island had no permanent inhabitants, maintaining a permanent settlement on this island had become a financial burden for the English Company. Therefore the English Company began experimenting with methods of colonial development as done in the English colonies of the Atlantic world. The company struggled to attract voluntary migrants from England. The people were attracted largely towards the destinations in North America and the Caribbean.2

The early colonization of St. Helena by the English Company in Madras had begun in 1654. An enslaved women’s involvement in medicine had been reported from Madras in 1654. A black Hindu woman from Santhome of Mylapore was brought in to St. Helena to perform an abortion of one of the English factor’s wives.3 Further the company also dispatched a party to settle at St. Helena from England in December 1658.

It is recorded that a Tamil male was forcefully brought from Fort St. George Madras to St. Helena December 1676 and finds mention. It is said that if his complaint reached the king of England, there could be problems to the English factor at Fort St. George.4 Slaves were purchased in Madras in 1679-80 and these child slaves were employed for domestic purposes.5

Some of the slaves were converted in Madras and this posed problems and difficulties. In 1678 Padre Antonio Luis of Santhome of Mylapore administered baptism to a slave who belonged to Nunes Valentine who was then living in the English settlement of Madras. The missionary was asked to leave the place at the earliest and the slave boy was confined for 18 days by the English Governor and council of Madras.6 Slave deeds in Madras were executed in Portuguese language. The scribe who wrote the sale deed in 1678 was paid two panams for each transaction.7

The directors of the English Company in London wrote in early August 1683 to their English factor in Fort St. George in Madras asking to explain why they had no thoughts of making a large sugar plantation with mills and sugar houses at St. Helena for the Company, and also a large great indigo plantation. Hence they were asked to explain the details.8 It was believed by the English Company at that time that there would be a good market for sugar in southern Persia (Iran) and also for indigo to be produced on St. Helena.9

Between June 1683 and April 1684 the English Company directors instructed its overseas employees to supply planters on St. Helena with useful seeds and plants of India, horses and tools from England, bricks from southern Persia, hard wood from Bengal for use as rollers in the sugar mills, oxen from India to drive the mills and broad beans to feed the growing enslaved population.10 The English Company directors again wrote in February 1684 to officials in Madras and said that they preferred the enslaved workers who were able to speak either English or Portuguese to be transported from Madras, the lingua franca of Madras to enable them to communicate with planters and overseers and better impart their knowledge and skills.11

The company directors were of the opinion that the soil of St. Helena was fit for the production of commodities of a richer nature like potatoes and yams for the company use than cattle. They ordered ten black native slaves above sixteen years old to be sent on every ship sailing from Fort St. George in Madras to St. Helena.12 It was planned that the slaves brought were to be sold on credit to the poor planters of the island. This was to enable them to communicate with planters and overseers and better impart their knowledge and skills.13

The servants of the English East India Company in Madras were not willing to transport slaves owing to the existence of a ban on slave exports by the native rulers. The status quo had been maintained and it continued till 1682. However, export of slaves from Madras was sanctioned in 1683 by the English Governor and Council in Fort St. George when political conditions changed since Aurangzeb the Mughal ruler extended his rule in the region. Further one notices the discussion that had been made about the benefits of bringing the slaves to the island.14

A report of 1683 mentions the great number of slaves exported from Madras.15 On 21 June 1686 one finds that 100 slaves were exported from Madras to St. Helena.16 In September 1687 one finds that 665 slaves registered for export from Madras. An export duty of one pagoda on each slave was levied at that time.17

In 1687 the English Company directors dispatched to the authorities in Fort St. George, a 30-year old book containing Dutch methods of commerce and governance in the East.18 It was stolen and seized from a Dutch ship. The manual contained instructions in the Dutch design regarding new commercial and diplomatic strategies in order to push and enter the markets in the East. This was to be followed in response to English strategies with revisions in their own policies. The officials in Fort St. George acknowledged this since it helped to reformulate their policies and politics.19

The Directors in London sent an order in 1688 to transport slaves from Madras to St. Helena. This was made with a view to sell slaves to the free inhabitants so that plantation works could be executed.20 Slaves from Madras and slaves received from Africa were employed in the farms in St. Helena. In one instance it is reported that an African (coffree) slave had escaped after having murdered a Tamil slave hailing from Madras. It is mentioned that the murder took place after a conflict over sticks of stolen sugar cane. The African slave could not be arrested because he had continued to live somewhere nearby, without returning to the enclosure of the African slaves. It is also said that at night he was fed secretly by the African community.21

The English Company records mention in 1709 that a plain near Sandy Bay on the south coast of St. Helena was fit for plantation development.22 Tamil slaves employed in St. Helena were of good conduct and so it is mentioned that many slaves of Madras in 1712 were freed by some of their owners at their will. Further, by this time, slaves could not be obtained for export from Madras to St. Helena.23

THE ENGLISH COMPANY SLAVE TRADE FROM
MADRAS TO BENGKULU ON THE WEST COAST
OF SUMATRA FOR SHIPYARD WORKS, 1682-1748

The English East India Company established a factory at Bengkulu (Bencoolen/Benkulen) on Sumatra’s west coast as part of its plan to secure supplies of pepper. The settlement was initially known as York Fort and subsequently called Fort Marlborough. The Dutch Company factory at Priaman began to monopolize the pepper trade and this prompted the English Company directors to decide in August 1687 to concentrate their Sumatran operations at Bengkulu.

In the beginning the directors authorized the officials at St. Helena to supply slaves to Bengkulu if they had any extra ones. It is found in a record that 30 slaves had already been sent from Madras. It is also mentioned that the English had endured suffering during the voyage from Madras to Sumatra.24 This evidence suggests that the English Company in Madras evinced interest and so it shipped slaves to satisfy the demand for labour in Sumatra.

In 1682, slave traders in Madras brought children who were stolen from the villages around in large numbers. As the female children had constituted the majority of slaves for export, the English Company decided not to export child slaves to Bengkulu.25 According to orders issued, the English settlement of Bengkulu was subordinated to Madras in 1685. Slaves of the English Company in Madras were involved in the construction, repair, and loading of ships in Madras. The company directors in London had instructed the officials at Fort St. George in 1685 to train their slaves in carpentry in preparation to establish a large shipyard.26 The English continued to purchase slaves as on 21 June 1686 during the time of famine.27

On 11 October 1686 200 slaves were exported from Madras to Aceh and Kedah.28 Dampier had noted that a new type of paddy cultivation had been introduced into Aceh. Hence the slaves brought from the Coromandel Coast by English traders were employed in the fields.29

On 8 September 1687 100 slaves were exported from Madras to Bengkulu. These slaves were obtained at a profit during a famine in the region when slaves were being sold by family members.30 These slaves were intended to serve as soldiers in Sumatra.31 The English Company records in September 1687 mention the export of 665 slaves in the ships that sailed from Madras to Bengkulu.32 Slaves from Madras were sent again in a ship along with seven more coffree (African) soldiers who reached Madras in November 1693. Slaves purchased were sent in March 1694 and in January 1696 to Bengkulu.33

The living conditions of the Madras slaves in Bengkulu had been noticed in records. A report in 1709 stated that the slaves were very poorly clothed because varieties of cloth suitable for slaves had not reached from Madras. This prompted the English Company officials to purchase locally produced variety of ordinary ginghams as a temporary solution to sort out the problem.34 Company officials brought slaves individually and in 1712, one finds mention of a Tamil male named January who was 25 years old, sold for $50.35

The local English Company officials emphasized in 1713 that both the African and Indian slaves from Madras were to be viewed like men and women and not slaves. But the directors in London pressed their company employees in Sumatra and said that their labourers were men and women though slaves. Hence they asked them to be used humanely according to their circumstances and not to be treated badly and worse than brutes.36

Slaves from Madras were exported to Bengkulu. One finds 60 slaves reached in 1713. Again in 1730 one finds 12 slaves shipped. Later in 1742 one finds transportation of 18 slaves and 12 slaves in 1748. The slave supplies were found inadequate in Sumatra owing to heavy demand for work at the dock. Hence in 1731 the English in Bengkulu secured the services of people including a boatman named Andrew from Madras sold for $60.37 The lack of supply of cloth from Madras for slaves had posed serious problems. It continued, time and again reported in 1711, 1715, 1726 and 1727.38 The much needed supplies did not arrive from Madras in 1746 which led to a reduction in slaves’ monthly rice allowance.39

Crimes committed by slaves came to be reported. In 1735, a slave woman named Hannah was found guilty of poisoning the armourer of the fort. Hence she was sentenced to be flogged 39 times each at three places on her body. She was kept in iron chains and later exiled to Madras in a ship.40 The Madras slave escaped owing to ill-treatment had been recorded in Bengkulu. One finds that eight Madras slaves had escaped from the fort’s hospital in 1737. However these fugitive slaves were later recovered.41

To conclude it may be said that the English East India Company exported slaves from its trading factory of Fort St. George, Madras to Bengkulu in Sumatra and these slaves were used there. The records reveal that the company drew slaves from a catchment area to satisfy the demand for labour in its far-flung commercial empire. The policies and practices regarding the treatment of company slaves illustrate the company’s role in the development of increasingly interconnected forced labour trades during the period.

NOTES

1. B. Natarajan, ‘Slave Trade in Madras’, The Madras Tercentenary Commemoration Volume, Madras, 1939, p. 249.

2. Stephen Royle, The Company’s Island: St. Helena, Company Colonies and the Colonial Endeavour, London, Bloomsbury, 2007, p. 44.

3. British Library (hereafter BL), London, India Office Records (hereafter IOR), G/19/1, fls. 16-17, 5 May 1655.

4. BL, IOR, E/3/88, fl.180, Letter from London to Fort St. George, 15 December 1676.

5. Records of Fort St. George, Diary and Consultation Book, 1662-1746, 1749-57, ed. C.M. Schmidt, J.J. Cotton, A.V. Venkatarama Ayyar, B.S. Baliga et al., 90 vols., Madras, 1910-53 (hereafter DCB), 1679-80, p. 164.

6. DCB, 1678, p. 136.

7. DCB, 1678, pp. 61-2.

8. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 95, London to St. Helena, 1 August 1683.

9. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 175, London to St. Helena, 1 April 1684.

10. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 83, London to Fort St. George, 13 June 1683; E/3/90, fls. 95-6, London to St. Helena, 1 August 1683; E/3/90, fl. 159, London to Bengal, 5 March 1683/84; E/3/90, fl. 174, 178-9, London to St. Helena, 5 April 1684; IOR B/37, fl. 148, 225.

11. BL, IOR, E/3/ 90, fl. 154, London to Fort St. George, 29 February 1684; E/3/90, fl. 159, London to Bengal, 5 March 1684.

12. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 83, London to Fort St. George, 13 June 1683; E/3/90, fl. 91, London to St. Helena, 1 August 1683.

13. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 154, London to Fort St. George, 29 February 1684.

14. BL, IOR, E/3/90, fl. 83, London to Fort St. George, 13 June 1683.

15. Basanta Kumar Basu, ‘Notes on Slave Trade and Slavery in India during the Early Days of John Company’, Muslim Review, Calcutta, vol. 4, 1930, p. 22.

16. BL, IOR, G/19/4, fl. 33.

17. Henry Davison Love, Vestiges of Old Madras, 1640-1800, 4 vols., London, 1913, vol. I, pp. 545-6.

18. BL, IOR, E/3/91, fl. 213r, London to Fort St. George, 28 September 1687.

19. Ibid.

20. Records of FSG, Public Consultations, 1672-1750, 36 vols., Madras, 1910-38, see 15 February 1688, p. 30.

21. BL, IOR, G/35/4 (not foliated), 20 October 1699.

22. BL, St. Helena Consultation, 26 July 1709.

23. BL, Collet MS D. 1153/2, fl. 44, Letter to Nathaniel Hodges dated 2 November 1712. See also, H. Yule, ed., Diary of William Hedges, London, 1887-9, p. cccliv.

24. BL, IOR, E/3/91, p. 378.

25. DCB, 1682, p. 70.

26. BL, IOR, E/3/91, fl. 35, Letter from London to Fort St. George, 16 March 1685.

27. BL, IOR, G/19/4, fl. 33, Letter dated 21 June 1686.

28. BL, G/19/4, fl. 68.

29. William Dampier, A New Voyage Around the World, London, 1695, p. 107.

30. BL, IOR, G/35/2, fls. 74-85v, Letter of Elihu Yale and Council at Fort St. George to Benjamin Bloome at Bencoulen, 8 November 1687.

31. Ibid.

32. DCB, 1687, p. 63.

33. Letters to Fort St George, 45 vols., Madras, 1916-32, vol. 5, 107-22 and 127-8, Letter from Bencoulen to Madras, 2 November 1693; See also, BL, IOR, G/35/3, fl. 216, 18 January 1696; H. Yule, ed., Diary of William Hedges, London, 1887-9, vol. II, p. ccclvi, 6 March 1694.

34. BL, IOR, G/35/56, Fort Marlborough Consultation (hereafter FMC), 19 November 1709.

35. BL, IOR, G/35/57, York Fort Consultation (hereafter YFC), 22 May 1712.

36. BL, IOR, E/3/87, fl. 208, Letter from London to Bantam, 18 January 1670/71; BL, IOR, E/3/98, fl. 14, Letter from London to Bencoolen, 20 March 1712/13.

37. BL, IOR, G/35/61, FMC, 29 September 1731.

38. BL, IOR, G/35/57, YFC, 3 July 1711, 27 June 1715; BL, IOR, G/ 35/59, FMC, 20 August 1726; G/35/60, FMC, 3 May 1727.

39. BL, IOR, G/35/64, p. 312.

40. BL, IOR, G/35/61, FMC, 21 April 1735, 28 April 1735.

41. BL, IOR, G/35/60, FMC, 24 October 1727; G/35/62, 1738 section, p. 118, and 1739 section, p. 15; G/35/75, p. 132.